本节我展示几例流密码的实际应用
In this segment, I want to give a few
examples of stream ciphers that are used in practice.
先讲两个古老的例子
I'm gonna start with two old
examples that actually are not
它们都不应被用在新系统里了。
不过，它们依然被广泛使用着
supposed to be used in new systems.
But nevertheless, they're still fairly
先简单提一下术语，让大家熟悉一下概念
widely used, and so I just want to mention
the names so that you're familiar with
第一个要说的流密码叫做RC4
these concepts. The first stream cipher I
want to talk about is called RC4, designed
于1987年设计，我高度地描述一下
back in 1987. And I'm only gonna give you
the high-level description of it, and then
然后我们讨论RC4的一些弱点，就此抛弃之
we'll talk about some weaknesses of RC4
and leave it at that. So RC4 takes a
RC4的种子大小可变，例如可以是128位
variable size seed, here I just gave
as an example where it would take 128
它将被用做流密码的密钥
bits as the seed size, which would then
be used as the key for the stream cipher.
RC4做的第一件事，将128位密钥
扩展成2048位
The first thing it does, is it expands the
128-bit secret key into 2,048 bits, which
也就是内部发生器的状态
are gonna be used as the internal state
for the generator. And then, once it's done
完事后，它就执行一个非常简单的循环
this expansion, it basically executes a
very simple loop, where every iteration of
每一轮输出一个字节
发生器想运行几轮都可以的
this loop outputs one byte of output. So,
essentially, you can run the generator for
一轮产生一个字节。RC4挺流行的
as long as you want, and generate one byte
at a time. Now RC4 is actually, as I said,
实际上HTTPS里RC4就很常见
fairly popular. It's used in the HTTPS
protocol quite commonly actually.
目前，Google在HTTPS中使用RC4
These days, for example, Google uses RC4 in its
HTTPS. It's also used in WEP as we
RC4也被用在上节里的WEP协议中
当然在WEP中RC4使用不当
discussed in the last segment, but of
course in WEP, it's used incorrectly and
导致其一点都不安全。几年后
it's completely insecure the way it's used
inside of WEP. So over the years,
RC4的一些弱点被找到
some weaknesses have been found in RC4, and as a
result, it's recommended that new projects
所以新项目中不推荐使用RC4
而应使用更为现代的伪随机数发生器
actually not use RC4 but rather use a more
modern pseudo-random generator as we'll
我们将在本节末讨论之
我就谈谈RC4的两个弱点
discuss toward the end of the segment. So
let me just mention two of the weaknesses.
首先，很奇怪地，如果你看
RC4输出的第二个字节
So the first one is, it's kind of bizarre
basically, if you look at the second byte
第二个字节有点不均匀
of the output of RC4. It turns out the
second byte is slightly biased. If RC4 was
如果RC4是完全随机的，
第二个字节等于0的概率
completely random, the probability that the
second byte happens to be equal to zero
应该严格为1/256，因为有256种字节值
would be exactly one over 256. There are
256 possible bytes, the probability that
等于0的概率应为1/256
不过RC4里的概率
it's zero should be one over 256. It so
happens that for RC4 the probability is
却为2/256，如果大家使用RC4的输出
actually two over 256, which means that if
you use the RC4 output to encrypt a
来加密一段信息，第二个字节
就更有可能不会被加密
message, the second byte is likely to not
be encrypted at all. In other words it'll
换句话说，它以比正常情况多一倍的概率
与0异或
be XOR-ed with zero with twice the
probability that it's supposed to.
是2/256，而非1/256。顺带一提
So two over 256, instead of one over 256.
And by the way I should say that there's
第二个字节并非特例
第一和第三个字节
nothing special about the second byte. It
turns out the first and the third bytes
也不是均匀的。事实上，如果你使用RC4
are also biased. And in fact it's now
recommended that if you're gonna use RC4,
推荐忽略掉RC4输出的前256个字节
what you should do is ignore basically the
first 256 bytes of the output and just
从发生器产生的第257个字节开始
start using the output of the generator
starting from byte 257. The first couple
前面的字节是不均匀的，大家忽略
of bytes turned out to be biased, so you
just ignore them. The second attack that
第二个攻击是说，如果你看RC4的
一段很长的输出
was discovered is that in fact if you look
at a very long output of RC4, it so happens
会发现序列00出现的可能性更大
that you're more likely to get the
sequence 00. In other words, you're more
换句话说，16位2字节更有可能是00
likely to get sixteen bits, two bytes of
zero, zero, than you should. Again, if RC4
如果RC4是完全随机的，00出现的概率
was completely random, the probability of
seeing zero, zero would be exactly 1/256
应为1/256的平方。但其实RC4是不均匀的
偏差约为1/256的立方
squared. It turns out RC4 is a little
biased and the bias is 1/256 cubed. It
在RC4生成几G的数据后，这种偏差开始显现
turns out this bias actually starts after
several gigabytes of data are produced by
不过，有可以预测发生器的方法
RC4. But nevertheless, this is something
that can be used to predict the generator
它当然可以被用来区分
and definitely it can be used to
distinguish the output of the generator
发生器输出和真随机序列
00出现的概率比正常情况大
from a truly random sequence. Basically the
fact that zero, zero appears more often
便是区分的依据。在上一节中
than it should is the distinguisher. And
then in the last segment we talked about
我们讨论了针对密钥关联的攻击
用来攻击WEP的
related-key attacks that were used to
attack WEP, that basically say that
如果使用的密钥之间紧密联系
if one uses keys that are closely related
to one another then it's actually possible
实际上是可能还原根密钥的
那么这些就是RC4的弱点
to recover the root key. So these are the
weaknesses that are known of RC4 and, as a
所以不推荐在新系统中使用RC4
result, it's recommended that new systems
actually not use RC4 and instead use a
换更现代的伪随机数发生器会更好
好的，我想说的第二个例子
modern pseudo-random generator. Okay,
second example I want to give you is a
是已被完全破解的，用于加密DVD电影的
badly broken stream cipher that's used for
encrypting DVD movies. When you buy a DVD
大家在商店买的DVD，上面的电影
是被用流密码加密过的
in the store, the actual movie is
encrypted using a stream cipher called the
叫做混淆系统CSS，作为流密码
CSS已被完全破解
content scrambling system, CSS. CSS turns
out to be a badly broken stream cipher,
我们可以轻易破解之
我将展示攻击算法的工作原理
and we can very easily break it, and I
want to show you how the attack algorithm
这样大家可以体会一下攻击算法的威力
works. We're doing it so you can see an
example of an attack algorithm, but in
事实上有很多系统正是使用这个攻击
fact, there are many systems out there
that basically use this attack to decrypt
来破解DVD的。CSS流密码是基于
一些硬件设计者的偏好
encrypted DVDs. So the CSS stream cipher
is based on something that hardware
它是面向硬件设计的流密码
designers like. It's designed to be a
hardware stream cipher that is supposed to
它应是易于硬件实现的
be easy to implement in hardware, and is
based on a mechanism called a linear
它是基于线性反馈移位寄存器(LFSR)的
feedback shift register. So a linear
feedback shift register is basically a register
LFSR是一由若干单元组成的寄存器
每个单元含一位
that consists of cells where
each cell contains one bit. Then basically
接着对特定的单元有出头
不是全部单元都有
what happens is there are these taps into
certain cells, not all the cells, certain
特定位置的叫出头，然后
这些出头被异或
positions are called taps. And then these
taps feed into an XOR and then at
在每一个时钟周期，寄存器向左移一位
every clock cycle, the shift register
shifts to the left. The last bit falls off
(完了，左右不分了。。)
最右位被丢弃，而异或结果被当作第一位
and then the first bit becomes the result
of this XOR. So you can see that
可见这个机制易于实现
硬件上仅需极少的电路实现
this is a very simple mechanism to
implement, and in hardware takes very few
只有右移，丢最右位
transistors. Just the shift right, the
last bit falls off and the first bit just
以及将之前的位的异或结果当第一位
becomes the XOR of the previous
bits. So the seed for this LFSR
LFSR的种子就是寄存器的初始状态
basically, is the initial state of the
LFSR.
这是很多流密码的基础，这有几个例子
And it is the basis of a number of stream
ciphers. So here are some examples. So, as
DVD加密使用了两个LFSR
待会告诉大家是怎么工作的
I said, DVD encryption uses two LFSRs.
I'll show you how that works in just a
GSM系统里的加密，比如A51和A52
second. GSM encryption, these are
algorithms called A51 and A52. And that
(GSM:全球移动通信)
这些使用三个LFSR。蓝牙加密
使用的算法叫做E0
uses three LFSRs. Bluetooth encryption is
an algorithm called, E zero. These are all
这些全是流密码，使用了4个LFSR
这些算法全部都被完全破解了
stream ciphers, and that uses four LFSRs.
Turns out all of these are badly broken,
加密流量时，它们不应被信任
and actually really should not be trusted
for encrypting traffic, but they're all
但是它们都被硬件实现了
所以现在改硬件有点困难
implemented in hardware, so it's a little
difficult now to change what the hardware
不过这些当中最简单的CSS，有一巧妙攻击
does. But the simplest of these, CSS,
actually has a cute attack on it, so let
我将告诉大家如何攻击
我们先看CSS的工作原理
me show you how the attack works. So,
let's describe how CSS actually works. So,
CSS的密钥是5个字节，40位
5乘8等于40
the key for CSS is five bytes, namely 40
bits, five times eight is 40 bits. The
之所以要限制到40位
reason they had to limit themselves to
only 40 bits is that DVD encryption was
是因为设计DVD加密算法时
美国出口法规定
designed at a time where U.S. Export
regulations only allowed for export of
出口的加密算法密钥只能是40位
crpyto algorithms where the key was
only 40 bits. So the designers of CSS were
所以CSS的设计者们只能使用极短的密钥
只有40位。他们是这样设计的
already limited to very, very short keys.
Just 40 bit keys. So, their design works
CSS使用两个LFSR，一个是17位LFSR
as follows. Basically, CSS uses two
LFSR's. One is a 17-bit LFSR. In other words,
也就是说寄存器含17位，另一个为25位
the register contains
17 bits. And the other one is a 25-bit LFSR,
略长些，25位寄存器
这些寄存器是这样取种子的
it's a little bit longer, 25-bit
LFSR. And the way these LFSRs are seeded
加密的密钥如下构成
is as follows. So the key for the
encryption, basically looks as follows.
(这样应该是种子seeds)
开头是1，然后联结密钥的前两个字节
You start off with a one, and you
concatenate to it the first two bytes of
这就构成了LFSR的初始状态
the key. And that's the initial state of the LFSR.
另一个寄存器也以类似的方式被初始化
And then the second LFSR basically is
intitialized the same way.
1联结上密钥的后三个字节
One concatenated the last three bytes of
the key. And that's
那就是LFSR的初始状态
前两字节16位
loaded into the initial state of the LFSR.
You can see that the first two bytes are
加上开头1一共是17位
sixteen bits, plus leading one, that's
seventeen bits overall, whereas the second
第二个寄存器是24+1=25位
注意我们使用了密钥的全部5个字节
LFSR is 24 bits plus one which is 25 bits.
And you notice we used all five bytes of
然后这些LFSR运行8轮
the key. So then these LFSRs are basically
run for eight cycles, so they generate
输出8位，然后它们在这里相加
eight bits of output. And then they go
through this adder that does basically
取模256。这个加法是模256的
addition modulo 256. Yeah so this is an
addition box, modulo 256. There's one more
还有一点，事实上加法要考虑前一分块的进位的
technical thing that happens. In fact let's
actually―also added is the carry from the
但这不重要，是不相关的细节而已
previous block. But that is not so
important. That's a detail that's not so
注意对每个分块，我们求模256和
relevant. OK, so every block, you notice
we're doing addition modulo 256 and
我们不考虑进位，进位以0或1的形式
we're ignoring the carry, but the carry is
basically added as a zero or a one to the
加给下一分块，对吧？
一轮输出一个字节
addition of the next block. Okay? And then
basically this output one byte per round.
当然，然后这个字节和
Okay, and then this byte is then of course
used, XOR-ed with the appropriate
电影数据里的字节进行异或加密
CSS是个很简单的流密码
byte of the movie that's being encrypted.
Okay, so it's a very simple stream
仅需少量硬件即可实现，速度快
cipher, it takes very little hardware to
implement. It will run fast, even on very
即使在很廉价的硬件上，也可加密电影
所以实际上它容易破解
cheap hardware and it will encrypt movies.
So it turns out this is easy to break
只需2的17次方的尝试。是这样做到的
in time roughly two to the seventeen.
Now let me show you how.
假设获取了加密后的电影数据
So suppose you
intercept the movies, so here we have an
希望能破解之。电影被全部加密了
encrypted movie that you want to decrypt.
So let's say that this is all encrypted so
你还不知道内容，但是
you have no idea what's inside of here.
However, it so happens that just because
由于DVD加密使用的MPEG文件
如果你知道明文的前缀
DVD encryption is using MPEG files, it so
happens if you know of a prefix of the
比如说前20个字节
plaintext, let's just say maybe this is
twenty bytes. Well, we know if you
如果你异或这两者
XOR these two things together,
so in other words, you do the XOR here,
你将得到PRG的最初输出分段
what you'll get is the initial
segment of the PRG. So, you'll get the
所以你可以得到CSS输出的前20个字节
即PRG的输出
first twenty bytes of the output of CSS,
the output of this PRG. Okay, so now
好，我们这样攻击它
现在我们有了输出的前20个字节
here's what we're going to do. So we have
the first twenty bytes of the output. Now
这样做：我们尝试2的17次方种
第一个LFSR的可能的初始状态
we do the following. We try all two to the
seventeen possible values of the first
也就2的17次方种，对每一种值
LFSR. Okay? So two to the seventeen
possible values. So for each value, so for
对每一种17位LFSR的可能初始状态
each of these two to the seventeen initial
values of the LFSR, we're gonna run the
我们运行LFSR以生成20个字节，对吧？
有第一个LFSR生成20个字节
LFSR for twenty bytes, okay? So we'll
generate twenty bytes of outputs from this
每次都先假设2的17次方种之一
的可能初始状态
first LFSR, assuming―for each one of the
two to the seventeen possible settings.
记得我们有全部的CSS输出
Now, remember we have the full output of
the CSS system. So what we can do is we
我们可以将得到的输出减去
第一个LFSR输出的20个字节
can take this output that we have. And
subtract it from the twenty bytes that we
事实上如果我们对初始状态的猜测
是正确的
got from the first LFSR, and if in fact our
guess for the initial state of the first
我们得到的应该是第二个寄存器的
LFSR is correct, what we should get
is the first twenty-byte output of the
前20字节的输出，对吧？
这是根据CSS定义来的
second LFSR. Right? Because that's by
definition what the output of the CSS
实际上看20字节序列
system is. Now, it turns out that looking
at a 20-byte sequence, it's very easy
很容易判断这20个字节是否来自
一个25位的LFSR的输出
to tell whether this 20-byte sequence
came from a 25-bit LFSR or not. If it
如果不是，说明我们对17位寄存器的
猜测是错误的
didn't, then we know that our guess
for the 17-bit LFSR was
那我们就再猜一次，等等
incorrect and then we move on to the next
guess for the 17-bit LFSR and
直到最终猜对为止
the next guess and so on and so forth.
Until eventually we hit the right initial
实际上我们会得到
state for the 17-bit LFSR, and
then we'll actually get, we'll see that
我们得到的20字节的可能的输出
the 20 bytes that we get as the
candidate output for the 25-bit LFSR is
事实上是25位LFSR的一个可能输出
in fact a possible output for a 25-bit LFSR.
And then, not only will we have
这样，我们不仅能学到17位
LFSR的正确的初始状态
learned the correct initial state for the
17-bit LFSR, we will have also
我们还能学到25位寄存器的初始状态
learned the correct initial state of the
25-bit LFSR. And then we can predict the
这样我们就能预测CSS剩余的输出了
当然，用它也就能解密整个电影了
remaining outputs of CSS, and of course,
using that, we can then decrypt the rest of
我们可以还原整个明文。好
the movie. We can actually recover the
remaining plaintext. Okay. This is
这也是我们之前讲过的
讲得略快，但愿说得清
things that we talked about before. So, I
said this a little quick, but hopefully,
流密码这里我们有道家庭作业
it was clear. We're also going to be doing
a homework exercise on this type of stream
大家会领悟到这些攻击算法的工作原理
ciphers and you'll kind of get the point
of how these attack algorithms
还有一点，有许多开源系统
work. And I should mention that there are
many open-source systems now that actually
是用这个方法解密CSS密文的
use this method to decrypt CSS-encrypted
data. Okay, so now that we've seen two
看完了两个渣例子，我们来看
更好的例子
weak examples, let's move on to better
examples, and in particular the better
有个更好点的伪随机数发生器
来自eStream项目
pseudo-random generators come from what's
called the eStream Project. This is a
这是个2008年完结的项目
他们给出了5种不同的流密码
project that concluded in 2008, and they
qualify basically five different stream
不过我这里只讲一种
ciphers, but here I want to present just
one. So first of all the parameters for
首先，这些流密码的参数
有点跟之前的不一样
these stream ciphers are a little
different than what we're used to. So these
同样地，这些流密码也有种子
stream ciphers as normal they have a seed.
But in addition they also have, what's
不过它们还有一个新鲜值
表示现在马上就要用
called a nonce and we'll see what a
nonce is used for in just a minute. So
它们输入种子和新鲜值
我们待会看怎么用新鲜值
they take two inputs a seed and a nonce.
We'll see what the nonce is used for in
当然它们产生一个很大的输出
just a second. And the of course they
produce a very large output, so n here is
这里n远远大于s，现在
新鲜值的意思是
much, much, much bigger than s. Now, when
I say nonce, what I mean is a value that's
只要密钥定下来，永不重复的值
待会再详细解释
never going to repeat as long as the key
is fixed. And I'll explain that in more
现在就把它当作一个永不重复的唯一值
detail in just a second. But for now, just
think of it as a unique value that never
只要密钥不变，当然，一旦你有这个PRG
repeats as long as the key is the same.
And so of course once you have this PRG,
你可以像流密码一样加密，不过
you would encrypt, you get a stream cipher
just as before, except now as you see, the
PRG需要密钥和新鲜值两个输入
PRG takes as input both the key and the
nonce. And the property of the nonce is
输入表示成(k,r)，(密钥,新鲜值)
这个有序对永不重复
that the pair, k comma r, so the key comma
the nonce, is never―never repeats. It's
它不被多次使用。底线是可以重复使用密钥
never used more than once. So the bottom
line is that you can reuse the key, reuse
因为新鲜值确保了有序对唯一
(k,r)只使用一次
the key, because the nonce makes the
pair unique, because k and r are only
它们是唯一的，好，这个新鲜值有点巧
used once. I'll say they're unique. Okay
so this nonce is kind of a cute trick that
这样我们不必每次换密钥了
saves us the trouble of moving to a new
key every time. Okay, so the particular
我想给大家看一下eStream的一个特别例子
叫做Salsa20
example from the eStream that I want to
show you is called Salsa twenty. It's a
这是一个同时面向硬件和软件设计的流密码
stream cipher that's designed for both
software implementations and hardware
有点意思。有些流密码是为软件设计的
implementations. It's kind of interesting.
You realize that some stream ciphers are
比如RC4，一切设计
designed for software, like RC4.
Everything it does is designed to make
都是为了让软件跑得快
还有的流密码是为硬件设计的
software implementation run fast, whereas
other stream ciphers are designed for
比如CSS，使用LFSR，特别面向硬件
hardware, like CSS, using an LFSR that's
particularly designed to make hardware
硬件实现的开销小
能同时面向软件硬件设计
implementations very cheap. It's also, the
nice thing about that is that it's
那就更好了，这样两者实现都容易
designed so that it's both easy to
implement it in hardware and its software
那么我来解释一下Salsa的工作原理
implementation is also very fast. So let
me explain how Salsa works. Well, Salsa
Salsa输入128位或256位密钥
我只看128为版本的Salsa
takes either 128 or 256-bit keys. I'll
only explain the 128-bit version of Salsa.
输入密钥，如前所说，也输入一个新鲜值
So this is the seed. And then it also
takes a nonce, just as before, which
新鲜值64位，然后产生一个大的输出
happens to be 64 bits. And then it'll
generate a large output. Now, how does it
怎么来的？函数如下定义
actually work? Well, the function itself
is defined as follows. Basically, given
给定密钥和新鲜值，生成一个很长的
伪随机序列
the key and the nonce, it will generate a
very long, well, a long pseudorandom
要有多长有多长。使用的函数记为H
sequence, as long as necessary. And it'll do
it by using this function that I'll denote by
函数H有三个输入：密钥种子k
H. This function H takes three inputs.
Basically the key. Well, the seed k,
新鲜值r和一个步骤计数器
the nonce r, and then a counter that
increments from step to step. So it goes
计数器可以从0到1，2，3，4...
from zero to one, two, three, four as long as
we need it to be. Okay? So basically,
通过用H计算(k,r)，使用计数器
by evaluating this H on this k r, but using
this incrementing counter, we can get a
我们可以获得足够长的序列
现在我需要描述函数H的工作过程
sequence that's as long as we want. So all
I have to do is describe how this function
搞起，它是如下工作的
H works. Now, let me do that here for you.
The way it works is as follows. Well, we
我们先把状态扩充至64字节长
start off by expanding the states into
something quite large which is 64 bytes
这样操作：开始时我们定个常数
long, and we do that as follows. Basically
we stick a constant at the beginning, so
比如Tau0，是个四字节的常数
there's tau zero, these are four bytes,
it's a four byte constant, so the spec for
Salsa的说明书上给定了Tau0的值
Salsa basically gives you the value for
tau zero. Then we put k in which is
然后取16字节的密钥k
然后还要定另外一个四字节的常数
sixteen bytes. Then we put another
constant. Again, this is four bytes. And
说明书上也给定了这个常数
as I said, the spec basically specifies
what this fixed constant is. Then we put
然后我们取8字节的新鲜值
然后再取索引，也就是计数器
the nonce, which is eight bytes. Then we
put the index. This is the counter zero,
0,1,2,3,4..也是8字节长
然后还要取另外一个常数Tau2
one, two, three, four, which is another
eight bytes. Then we put another constant
四字节长，然后再次取密钥
tau two, which is another four bytes.
Then we put the key again, this is another
这就是另一个16字节。最后取第三个常数Tau3
sixteen bytes. And then finally we put the
third constant, tau three, which is
(其实Tau3是第四个常数)
也是四字节。好了，如果把这些加一起
你就得到了64字节的状态
another four bytes. Okay so as I said, if you
sum these up, you see that you get 64
我们将密钥、新鲜值和计数器
扩张成了64字节
bytes. So basically we've expanded the key
and the nonce and the counter into 64
我猜密钥被重复使用了两次了
bytes. Basically the key is repeated twice
I guess. And then what we do is we apply a
然后我们应用函数h
function, I'll call this functional little h.
Okay, so we apply this function, little h.
这个函数是个一一对应的双射
由64字节映射到64字节
And this is a function that's one to one
so it maps 64 bytes to 64 bytes. It's a
完全可逆的函数，对吧？函数h可逆
completely invertible function, okay? So
this function h is, as I say, it's an
给输入，得输出
invertable function. So given the input
you can get the output and given the
给输出，也能得输入
这个特别的设计易于硬件实现
output you can go back to the input. And
it's designed specifically so it's a- easy
在x86机上特别容易实现
to implement in hardware and b- on an x86,
it's extremely easy to implement because
因为x86的SSE2指令支持该函数h的
x86 has this SSE2 instruction set which
supports all the operations you need to do
全部操作。很快很快，Salsa是很快的流密码
for this function. It's very, very fast.
As a result, Salsa has a very fast stream
它将重复这个操作
cipher. And then it does this basically
again and again. So it applies this
反复应用函数h，获得64字节，等等
function h again and it gets another 64
bytes. And so on and so forth, basically
基本上要来10次。好，这里重复10次
it does this ten times. Okay so the whole
thing here, say repeats ten times, so
应用函数h十次，本身并不随机
basically apply h ten times. And then by
itself, this is actually not quite random.
并不随机是因为之前说了H是可逆的
It's not gonna look random because like we
said, H is completely invertable. So given
给定最后的输出，很容易求h的逆
然后回到最初的输入
this final output, it's very easy to
just invert h and then go back to the original
测出输入的正确结构
inputs and then test that the input has
the right structure. So you do one more
再做一件事就够了，将输入和输出异或
thing, which is to basically XOR the
inputs and the final outputs. Actually,
不好意思，还不是异或，是加法
逐字进行的加法
sorry. It's not an XOR. It's actually an
addition. So you do an addition word by
如果是64字节，你要4字节一次地加
word. So if there are 64 bytes, you do a
word-by-word addition four bytes at a
最终得到64字节的输出，完事
time, and finally you get the 64-byte
output, and that's it. That's the whole
这就是整个伪随机数发生器
那是整个函数h
pseudo-random generator. So that, that's
the whole function, little h. And as I
如前所说，整个机制在于函数H
explained, this whole construction here is
the function big H. And then you evaluate
当你计数器加一，0,1,2,3..
big H by incrementing the counter I from
zero, one, two, three onwards. And that
它就会给你一个伪随机数序列
要有多长有多长
will give you a pseudo-random sequence
that's as long as you need it to be. And
目前Salsa还没有重大攻击
basically, there are no signifigant
attacks on this. This has security that's
其安全性非常接近于2的128次方
之后我们再详细讨论之
very close to two to the 128. We'll see
what that means more precisely later on.
Salsa是非常快的流密码
于硬件和软件而言
It's a very fast stream cipher, both in
hardware and in software. And, as far as
作为流密码，它似乎是无法预测的
we can tell, it seems to be unpredictable
as required for a stream cipher. So I
应该说eStream项目有5个这样的流密码
should say that the eStream project
actually has five stream ciphers like
我只讲了Salsa，因为我觉得它最美观
this. I only chose Salsa 'cause I think
it's the most elegant. But I can give you
我可以给大家一些性能参数
这些是在2.2GHz的x86机上的
some performance numbers here. So you can
see, these are performance numbers on a
性能值。可以看到RC4其实是最慢的
2.2 gigahertz, you know, x86 type machine.
And you can see that RC4 actually is the
因为RC4并没有充分利用硬件
slowest. Because essentially, well it
doesn't really take advantage of the
它只有字节操作，还有很多浪费的循环
hardware. It only does byte operations.
And so there's a lot of wasted cycles that
但eStream，包括Salsa
aren't being used. But the eStream
candidates, both Salsa and other
以及其他候选机制比如Sosemanuk
应该说它们是eStream优胜者
candidate called Sosemanuk. I should say these
are eStream finalists. These are
它们是eStream批准的流密码机制
actually stream ciphers that are approved
by the eStream project. You can see that
可以看到它们的性能很高
每秒能处理643M字节的数据
they have achieved a significant rate.
This is 643 megabytes per second on this
足以对付电影了。还有些很好的指标
architecture, more than enough for a movie
and these are actually quite impressive
现在大家看了两个古老的流密码
rates. And so now you've seen examples of
two old stream ciphers that shouldn't be
不再能使用的，以及针对它们的攻击
大家还看了现代的流密码
used, including attacks on those stream ciphers.
You've seen what the modern stream ciphers
特点是这个新鲜值
大家也看到现代流密码的性能了
look like with this nonce. And you
see the performance numbers for these
所以如果需要流密码时
modern stream ciphers so if you happen to
need a stream cipher you could use one of
可以使用eStream推荐的方案，比如Salsa
the eStream finalists. In particular you
could use something like Salsa.